Oh, my friends and welcome again to the complete data structure and algorithms course.
And this video we are going to solve.
Exercise number eighty six.
So in this exercise, we are asked to create binary search tree and implement its operation in Java.
So I will create a new Java class called Binary Search Tree.
By the way, you can download all of the source code of the previous exercises from the Resources folder
inside Udemy course underneath every exercise.
We start as every class and every tree that we have created by creating the class.
Note that no structure for that tree.
It contained this new and key, and it contains the reference for the left and the right.
Now I will create a constructor for this so node and item, and we specify the key.
You can make it put the item.
Or I can put here the.
This thought gave equal to
the past key and left, equal to right, equal to none.
This is what we do when you see a tree.
We create the note that start by creating the key and in shallows the left and right pointers to not
know.
Note it's create the note through it for this, so I would create notes and a.
This is the object from class note and let's create to this constructor or binary search tree in the
constructor.
And when we created mining a search tree, just make the root equal to none.
OK, this is how we make the binary search a tree like that basic structure, their coding structure
and building block of our codes.
Let's try to make their methods for operation.
The first operation is the insert, so void insert.
I will insert the key.
Then we put root equal to insert.
I will call the method insert key in the root and the key.
This is just a like encapsulation or like wrapping for the function.
I can make directly insert key, but I preferred using this method in order to simplify without like
pressing the root and the key.
Every time, every time I pass, only the key.
So when I need to insert a new key, I directly call, insert and pass the key and insert key it directly.
Call this method insert key and pass that route again.
Now let's create this.
It will return and note it's returning Typekit the note.
So I will create node insert key stake into the perimeter of the node root and end key the return in
you node if the tree is empty.
So the first case creating new node
if.
If that tree is empty, if we are inserting the first note, if it would be equally cool to know as
a professional coder and data structure, an algorithm master, you should you should cover all the
possible ways possible the possibilities, all the possible and cover all the possibilities, all the
different cases, all the the like, the opportunities of the code.
So here we are returning the note.
If in, you know, if the tree is empty, so do it equal to new nodes and I've passed the key and the
return route.
This is when we have to cover that new node creation.
If there is nodes.
If.
That really is not and what we do.
We check if key.
Less than a.
The key what we do.
We go to the route to the left in order to insert it and we insert the key again, we called the method
to the route that left and key the or the very important note that we should always think about it and
remember N.B. as these, that the left is to the left notes is less than that route and the right up
three and the right notes values are greater than the Route four that we have used that encourage it.
And we see that the insert key has been called again, and that's the left again and again until we
have root equal to none and we make that execution.
So else
else, if the key greater than the key route, the key or comparing it with that, it would make the
same thing.
But now at the right side, equal uncertainty and in the road, the road, the tried and they're OK.
OK, now we return route.
This is very simple.
We check if it is less than the route.
We start comparing it, comparing it until we find the key.
And if we the key is greater than the route, a greater than the route, then it will go to that until
we find the route equal, equal to null.
And then we insert the note, OK?
This is how we insert that nodes in B Estes.
No, let's make that in order in order traversal because I need to use it in the Delete B. And we have
seen this in their previous videos.
How to delete the key from Dan from the BSD in order traversal because it's fairly simple.
And.
We we ensure that when we when we need to delete anything, we have three cases.
The first case is deleting the note with no children on it.
And the second case deleting the note that it has only one note.
And the third case is deleting a note from having children.
And we just need to make that reversal in the next successor.
So we are going to replace it with the successor to the next successor.
For that, we are going to use the in order traversal.
So in order method, also, this method will call in order.
Correct.
And that's the truth.
And I am going to create this method again, and it type void, extending type, void and best through
it.
And we check if Root does not equal to null.
Then in order in order to wreck again, we passed through the left system that allowed the Brent Allen
Brent Root the key, and we pass this
in order to print it in order again.
And we passed the rule thought, right, OK, this is how we in order traversal for their records,
why do we do this?
Because we are going to use it in the delete key?
So I will use Void Delete key.
I will get the key and key and key.
And again, I need the power to create a proper function.
A. Equal to delete key, I pass through it and the key I will create, delete, delete, wreck.
OK, I will create this function, no
route and key.
No, let's check for their for their deletion.
Please concentrate with me.
It's very, very simple if you understand it, and it's very complex if you don't understand.
We said that we have three cases.
The first case, if the three, if they're three at that node that we are going to delete, don't have
any children.
OK, so we start by checking if their route is equal to another empty, no return route.
OK.
We are deleting an empty three or a note that content does not contain any children.
Now, in order to delete anything and you know, we need to start finding the note first.
OK?
And then executing the deletion if key less than a rule turkey.
Then we use Route Dot left equal to delete the rack and we put route that left.
There's the key.
This is what we do if the key is less than the route key, the key of the route.
OK, so the key is on the left side because the left side, the left side of three is always less than
the root of the key.
OK.
No else.
If if you are checking if key greater than the route through Turkey, and we start by assigning the
route that right equal to delete Iraq, you wrote the right.
And we passed the key K else
else.
If the node is with only one child or no children, one child or no child.
This is the first and the second case.
So if the route that left equal equal to now, then I will return route or try because we are getting
the route to the right.
If it is to the left equals null, then we return the routes.
Not, but I as if.
Wrote Dot, right?
Equal equal to none.
Then we return, brought the left, OK.
This is the first is the first case and the second case in the deletion operation.
OK, so I want from you to go back to the video about the deletion operation.
And and in the beasties and try to understand the three cases because I am talking about the first case
and the second case is covered by this.
And now I'm going to solve the third case where if it is, then Node has two children.
OK, if Node has two children placed in order, I will put it again or to it or to save time for you.
That in honor, their successor
in position of node could be deleted.
So root, don't you get the key from the root and minimum value this is?
Then we get the minimum value.
I will create this method in next couple of minutes and delete now they're in order the successor from
its position.
Or try it be equal to delete key delete.
Correct Root.
Right.
And who thought, OK, OK,
now let's go back and return.
We need to return the root.
So this is what we need to make from this function is to return a return, the node that we are going
to still now find find in order successor.
We need to create that int minimum value.
It took it to the perimeter that nodes root and we start to make Int minimum value equal to all the
key.
And while we are going to look through the root, that left does not equal to none.
If we have, we are going to get the most left node in order to get minimum value.
OK.
And when the when we have when their root left does not equal to null.
So we have a new nodes, then minimum value equal to the root, the left the key.
And the root beer called to root the left, we return the minimum value.
OK.
This is how we find that in order success.
Now let's try to test our program.
And I for that, I will create the main method public static void, main string args.
I will create binary search tree to be equal to new binary search tree, and I will start inserting
the numbers insert
eight.
You copy and paste that.
Many times.
So eight, three, one six seven.
Then.
Fourteen and.
14 good.
Have three.
I need to insert Rs seven.
And for because I need to insert tape numbers.
In order to check that.
Time complexity that we are going to talk about in the next video in order traversal
three, though in order
and system that out, that Prince Allen.
After deleting them.
Three, The Delete Key 10 and system that allowed that print again,
the end or that traversal
three door in or that OK, no.
What we have in this three before running this program, I will lecture for you.
We have created.
There would hate.
We insert the cities, so three is less than eight, so I insert it to the left.
Insert one one is less than earpiece eight less than I was.
Sorry, one less than three.
Yes.
So I will insert it to the left of three.
I will insert six.
Six is greater than three, but less than eight.
So eight is less than eight or greater than six.
So I will put it here in this section and six is greater density.
So it will be like this.
OK, No.
Seven is less than eight.
So it would be in this section.
I will insert it to the right of three and to the right of six because if there's greater than.
Six.
Insert 10, 10 is greater than eight, so I will insert it here 14, insert 14 14 is greater than eight.
Yes, to the right.
14 greater than 10.
Yes, I would insert it also to that eight.
So I put it also 14.
And I will insert number four so far less than athiest to the left.
Three is four is greater than three.
Yes.
So I will insert that I six.
We have six.
Four is less than six or greater than six.
It's less than six.
So I will insert it right here.
OK.
This is what we have done in this section when we delete that key.
10.
So I will delete 10 14 were replaced this this deletion and 14 is the next successor of the 10.
So 14 would be the minimum value with the returning value of the mean value function that we have created
and 14 were replace that.
Now let's run and see our program.
We the three is that this is for the previous one.
I will run it again.
And there we go.
In order traversal of this tree, this is for that left arrow and right in order traversal.
This is for the left.
This is for the root.
And this is for that section.
After deleting then it would be one, three, four, six and seven.
This is the left section.
This is the root and this is the right.
Section 14 have been replaced then, and this is the algorithm behind making the binary search tree
and its operations deletion, insertion and search.
OK.
So thank you, guys.
I'm I'm waiting your comments.
I'm waiting your reviews and they help you rate great us five stars on Udemy to support us making new
videos and new exercises.